<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>&lt;img src=&#39;https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/logo.png&#39; style=&#39;width: 2.2em; height: 2.2em; border-radius: 30%;&#39;&gt; &lt;b&gt;AI Basics with AK&lt;/b&gt;</title>
<link>https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/</link>
<atom:link href="https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>LETS BREATHE DATA</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.550</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>What metrics to be chosen for classification modelling?</title>
  <dc:creator>Arun Koundinya Parasa</dc:creator>
  <link>https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/posts/metrics-classification-model/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This blog is a reponse to my team-mates questions posted on <code>Whatsapp</code>. I’m sharing my learnings and views for her each question in a seperate blog.</p>
<p>The biggest problem in classification modelling is to choose to a right metric for our problem at hand. Added to it, confusion matrix creates more confusion to us as it has more metrices that we imagine.</p>
<p>Lets cut-short this Arun. Ask <code>GenAI</code> tools we rely on it.</p>
<p>Go through this link of <code>ChatGPT</code> <a href="https://chat.openai.com/share/44e15e4f-ed46-49e4-97c7-232d98a3006c">response</a>. Definetly it will not help. Why?</p>
<p>Arun!!! prompt has to be more specific.</p>
<p>Okay! Okay! here it is with a revised prompt <a href="https://chat.openai.com/share/353267af-3dc4-449b-b0a1-2c4124a08ffe">response</a> from <code>ChatGPT</code>. Still it doesn’t help. Why?</p>
<p>It is because, we have humans need to decide what is the right metric. For this <code>Data Scientists</code> need to step up and do three important things which are usually not in their comfort zone:</p>
<ul>
<li>Speak to business stakeholders and understand their purpose again.</li>
<li>Also, understand how they will use our predictions.</li>
<li>Finally, before jumping into modelling and its coding; step-back and check whether dependant variable is defined as per business purpose and its corresponding usage.</li>
</ul>
<p>Step three is the recipe of experience i.e.; multiple tries and failures, which will not be discussed in this blog.</p>
<section id="confusion-matrix" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="confusion-matrix">Confusion Matrix</h2>
<p>Understanding details of <code>Confusion Matrix</code> is fundamental.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/posts/metrics-classification-model/confusion.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" width="857"></p>
<figcaption>Source : https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confusion_matrix</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Top four boxes is the result of prediction vs actual. Remaining boxes are dervied metrics based on the numbers.</p>
<p>Lets not bog down into these multiple metrices.</p>
</section>
<section id="simpler-thumb-rules" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="simpler-thumb-rules">Simpler Thumb Rules</h2>
<p>R</p>
</section>
<section id="how-to-choose" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-choose">How to Choose</h2>
<p>U</p>
</section>
<section id="why-stick-to-one-metric" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-stick-to-one-metric">Why stick to one metric?</h2>
<p>N</p>
</section>
<section id="can-we-change-the-metric-if-model-perform-is-poor" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-we-change-the-metric-if-model-perform-is-poor">Can we change the metric if model perform is poor?</h2>
<p>K</p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="ArunKoundinya/AIBasicswithAK" data-repo-id="R_kgDOLXPVRw" data-category="General" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOLXPVR84CdeVx" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="bottom" data-theme="purple_dark" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async="">
</script>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>classification</category>
  <category>modelling</category>
  <category>metrics</category>
  <guid>https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/posts/metrics-classification-model/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/posts/metrics-classification-model/confusion.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="89" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Does Data Scientists need to learn programming?</title>
  <dc:creator>Arun Koundinya Parasa</dc:creator>
  <link>https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/posts/learn-programming/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In an era of AI-enabled applications, chats, and programming (<a href="https://www.cognition-labs.com/blog-posts">now with Devin</a>), many youngsters and new entrants in the data science field assume that learning programming isn’t needed as almost all codes are available either on stack overflow or ChatGPT.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/posts/learn-programming/image.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" width="373"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>However, programming is not just a copy-and-paste activity. But it is an iterative process of four pieces:</p>
<ul>
<li>What to Code?</li>
<li>How to Code?</li>
<li>Test the Code?</li>
<li>Coding with-in limitations.</li>
</ul>
<p>Here, <code>What to Code</code> can be comprehended as an <code>Ideaation/Requirement Gathering and Planning</code> stage. Ideas can be either intrinsic or extrinsic, but the primary reward goes to both, i.e., the idea and proper planning. This is itself an intensive area where the know-how of coding is required; otherwise, the entire planning and further execution would fall into a fallacy.</p>
<p><code>How to Code</code> involves the <code>Coding the requirement, unit-testing and documentation</code> stage. Coding becomes an iterative step along with unit testing since our code changes should not hamper that part of the unit.</p>
<p><code>Test the Code</code> involves <code>Reviewing the code and completing the system-testing</code> stage. After we complete our code, it needs to be reviewed and refined by a senior programmer, ideally with an intention to optimize its performance and ensure that this particular fix will not hamper other units in the system.</p>
<p><code>Coding within limitation</code> involves the <code>Deployment and Maintenance</code> stage. After the entire coding, testing, and documentation are completed, Deployment becomes a central learning as initial programming doesn’t involve physical limitations. Deployment limitations, becomes an iterative process to enhance our coding.</p>
<p>If we understand this complete cycle of programming, we will learn that coding is not just a copy-paste job but often requires a thought process for maintenance of the code for long-term usage. However, there might be some applications ( we can term such applications as <code>AI-assisted</code> programming applications ) in the future that would help automate some of these. Still, it would require a keen human eye and thought process for thorough Deployment.</p>
<p>If you heard about Scrum masters or Scrum certification it is good else google it. These people are often valued because they are aware of the fundamentals of agile methodological practices, which involve iterative steps of planning, coding, testing, and maintenance.</p>
<section id="some-future-or-current-technologies" class="level5">
<h5 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="some-future-or-current-technologies">Some Future or Current Technologies</h5>
<ul>
<li>Coding Assistant:
<ul>
<li>Code Autocompletion ; Example: Github Copilot</li>
<li>AI Driven Automation Testing; Example: Testim</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Minimal Coding:
<ul>
<li>Low-Code Platform ; Example: Microsoft Power Apps</li>
<li>No-Code Platform; Example: Bubble, Google AppSheet</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Power Computing:
<ul>
<li>Serverless Computing ; Example: AWS Lambda</li>
<li>Edge Computing; Example: AWS IoT</li>
<li>Quantum Computing; Example: IBM Quantum</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>View them as assistants that will fasten our process such that a particular idea’s “time to market” will come down exponentially.</p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="ArunKoundinya/AIBasicswithAK" data-repo-id="R_kgDOLXPVRw" data-category="General" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOLXPVR84CdeVx" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="bottom" data-theme="purple_dark" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async="">
</script>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>programming</category>
  <guid>https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/posts/learn-programming/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/posts/learn-programming/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="123" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Does Data Scientists need to understand Domain Knowledge?</title>
  <dc:creator>Arun Koundinya Parasa</dc:creator>
  <link>https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/posts/is-domain-knowledge-important/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/posts/is-domain-knowledge-important/image.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" width="439"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This article intends to explain domain knowledge’s importance to freshers. The example provided below is from my own experience.</p>
<p>Businesses, by nature, want to earn profits, and why is it needed to make profits? From an employee perspective, the company gives salary and growth; from a company perspective, it intends to stay long, live and fresh as it grows.</p>
<p>Profit = Revenue - Cost</p>
<p>If the business needs to stay longer, the profit has to be on the positive side. It means either the revenue should increase or the cost should decrease; also, both can happen.</p>
<p>Let us explore simple business case scenarios that will help us learn why understanding the business comes first before we solutionize.</p>
<p>Case { Retail Store Business }</p>
<p>Assume that a data scientist was tasked to help the retail store stock the “right” quantity. By intuition, most “data scientists” consider the last X years of data for prediction. They may take various models from “simple averages” to “ARIMA” to “LSTM” and choose the best model based on the evaluation metrics like AIC or BIC, or MAPE. { Classic Time series modelling algorithms }</p>
<p>After this exercise, we will determine the quantity that could sell for the next period. Does it end here?</p>
<p>It would not, because we haven’t answered the business question of what should be the stock holding for the next period. i.e., how many goods should be stocked in the store?</p>
<p>Say, if we want to proceed with the model’s output itself. Since the model has inherent bias and variance, certain goods might get stocked out sooner, and others will not sell as predicted. { Alternatively, at times, the business could not procure the goods as indicated due to the cash flow constraint. Which we will discuss in other cases}</p>
<p>What happens if there is stock out; revenue drops. Alternatively, what happens if there is excess stock; cost increases. In both of these cases, the profit decreases.</p>
<p>Should we conclude that data science is not helping in this scenario? No, it isn’t.</p>
<p>It is just that it has not been adequately solutionized. So far, we have put the hat of “Machine Learning”, which needs to be started with the “Traditional Research” cap.</p>
<p>Under Traditional research, we may learn the following things: - Stock will come from warehouses every two days, for which the indent has to be shared a day earlier.</p>
<ul>
<li>In all case scenarios, a buffer or safety stock should be kept in the store for fast-moving items to avoid supply chain shocks.</li>
<li>Evading bull-whip effect, the probable forecast for certain goods must be shared with vendors for effective coordination.</li>
<li>A simulation must be constructed such that the stock at the store is not too high to avoid high business costs. Also, the store needs to maintain sufficient service levels(of the goods, i.e., stock availability) so the customer doesn’t face a bad experience.</li>
</ul>
<p>Based on these learnings, we will research any existing methodologies available to address these questions. Bingo!!</p>
<p>We would crack the solution by browsing the topics of Supply Chain Analytics or Operations Optimization.</p>
<p>Which will provide methods to arrive at Safety Stock, Re-order Level, Re-order Quantity and Service Levels.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/posts/is-domain-knowledge-important/safety_stock.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" width="437"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>From here, we can use ML ( Time Series Modelling ) to arrive at tomorrow’s prediction and perform a simulation ( Monte Carlo Simulation ) to arrive at service levels for different clusters ( K-Means Clustering ) of products. These outputs are fed into the above solution we saw in “Traditional Research”.</p>
<p>Later we wear the “Software Development” hat to fine-tune the coding and keep the end-to-end pieces in hands-off mode.</p>
<p>In this way, Data Scientists must change hats to complete the work.</p>
<p>In this case, we can clearly see that the “Traditional Research” hat is hugely needed to understand the “lay of the land”. Else the entire modelling effort would have faced an identity crisis.</p>
<p>Is there any defined prescription or rules to understand the lay of the land? The answer is NO. The long answer is</p>
<ul>
<li>Curiosity to learn about the domain.</li>
<li>Asking the business the right questions.</li>
<li>Doing personal research as, at times, business is driven by perceptions or experience. { Only a “fresh eye” brings a new perspective } - Learning what others have done already. There would have been plenty of research already available. <span style="font-size: small;">{ There is no need for new IP in most of the scenarios }</span></li>
<li>Learning Consultant frameworks like BCG Matrix, Product Life Cycle, Customer Life Cycle, etc., will help us think on alternative perspectives.</li>
</ul>
<p>There are several examples that I have faced personally in my early data science career, which told me the hard way about the importance of domain knowledge. The above example is one such classic. Stay tuned for more Data science news.</p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="ArunKoundinya/AIBasicswithAK" data-repo-id="R_kgDOLXPVRw" data-category="General" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOLXPVR84CdeVx" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="bottom" data-theme="purple_dark" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async="">
</script>



 ]]></description>
  <category>domain</category>
  <category>operations</category>
  <guid>https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/posts/is-domain-knowledge-important/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://arunkoundinya.github.io/AIBasicswithAK/blogs/posts/is-domain-knowledge-important/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="131" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
